Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Series 2: March of the French Army from Providence to Virginia, March 1781 - October 1781, 10 portfolios (1 partial)
  - 26. Plans des differents camps occupés par L'Armée aux orfres de M. Le Comte de Rochambeau, undated; more than 35 packets 32 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21)
    - 69. Camp à Prince-town, le 31 Aoust, 14 miles de Sommerset Court-house, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-24)
      Twenty-fourth Camp at Princeton. 31 August - 1 September 1781. Fourteen miles from the preceding camp at Somerset Courthouse. The "Collège" is Nassau Hall. The road leading in from the right of the map—here called the road from Somerset Courthouse, since that was the starting point of the day's March—is present Witherspoon Street. The army camped across the main road (Stockton Street, present U.S. Route 206) from the Richard Stockton residence (Morven), indicated here with its private entrance road (dotted lines). The camp extended across Mercer Street (which did not exist in 1781) on to grounds now occupied by the Princeton Theological Seminary. The crossroads at the lower part of the map is the present intersection of Nassau and Harrison Streets (Queenstown, Jugtown). The stream at the left of the map is Stony Brook, now enlarged at this point to form a part of Carnegie Lake.
      The army camped again in Princeton, 7-8 September 1782, presumably on this same site, since no new map was drawn for the series representing the 1782 camps.
      MS, No. 21-24. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 149]
    - 70. Camp à Trenton, le 1er Septembre, 12 1/2 miles de Princetown, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-25)
      Twenty-fifth Camp at Trenton. 1-2 September 1781. Twelve and a half miles from the preceding camp at Princeton. The stream flowing into the Delaware, shown on the map between the letters "n" and "t" of "Trenton," is the Assunpink. The infantry regiments camped beside the "Burlington Road" to the east of the Assunpink. The artillery unit was opposite the Trent House (then the residence of Colonel John Cox), shown here with its formally laid-out grounds.
      Dotted lines indicate the position occupied by one brigade a year later, when the army camped again in Trenton, 3-7 September 1782, on its northbound march.
      MS, No. 21-25. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 150]
    - 72. Camp à Read-Lion's Tavern, le 2 Septembre, 17 miles de Trenton, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-26)
      Twenty-sixth Camp at Red Lion Tavern. 2-3 September 1781. Seventeen miles from the preceding camp at Trenton. This was the last place the army camped before entering Philadelphia. The stream is Poquessing Creek, which flows into the Delaware. The tavern itself was in the depression formed by the creek, the camp on the higher ground beyond it. The road corresponds to U.S. Route 13, now paralleled by Interstate 95, which runs still closer to the Delaware.
      MS, No. 21-26. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 150]
    - 73. Camp à Philadelphie, le 3 Septembre, 14 miles de Read-Lion's Tavern. Le 4 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-27)
      Twenty-seventh Camp at Philadelphia. 3-6 September 1781. Fourteen miles from the preceding camp at Red Lion Tavern. The entire army was assembled here before resuming its march. The Lauzun Legion (both the infantry and the cavalry, or hussars), which had marched with the First Brigade after the Hudson crossing at King's Ferry, is shown on the right-hand side of the road. The widest of the streets shown (on a line with the second "i" in "Philadelphie" and the second "a" in "Delawar") is Market Street. The pontoon bridge across the Schuylkill was near the site of the present Market Street bridge.
      When the army stopped in Philadelphia a year later, the camp was on the northern outskirts of the city; see No. 137.
      MS, No. 21-27. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 150]
    - 74. Camp à Chester, le 5 Septembre, 16 miles de Philadelphie, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-28)
      Twenty-eighth Camp at Chester [in Pennsylvania]. 5-6 September 1781. Sixteen miles from Philadelphia. The street pattern shown here is still readily discernable in the heart of the modern city of Chester. The army's route from Philadelphia came in via present Market (formerly High) street. The first intersection shown corresponds to present Sixth Street, after which come Fifth, Fourth, the Market Square. The old market in the center of the intersection is represented on the map. Here the route turned sharp right along present Third Street and over the bridge across Chester Creek. The camp was southwest of the town on high ground along the road to Wilmington; the site is well inside the present city.
      A year later, when marching in the opposite direction, the army camped again at Chester, by divisions, on 30 August-2 September 1782. The camp was then northeast of the town, on the road to Philadelphia, between Ridley and Crum creeks; see No. 136.
      MS, No. 21-28. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 150-151]
    - 75. Camp à Willmington, le 6 Septembre, 11 1/2 miles de Chester, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-29)
      Twenty-ninth Camp at Wilmington [in Delaware]. 6 September 1781. Eleven and a half miles from the preceding camp at Chester. As shown on the road map above, No. 59, the Second Brigade did not camp in Wilmington but marched through and beyond the city to Newport, where it camped on 7 September. The route of the march through Wilmington and the campsite of the First Brigade there can be precisely determined by reference to the church and surrounding burial ground (small crosses) shown on the map. This is the Friends' Meeting House situated in the block bounded by West, Fifth, Fourth, and Pasture (present Washington) Streets; the original building was replaced by the present structure in the early nineteenth century. Thus the street at the top of the grid is Front Street, the one at right angles to it, far left, is Orange Street. The "Corderie," lower right, is a rope walk then on he property of Mordecai Woodward. A small dotted line shows the army's route: coming into town via a road passing from the Brandywine Creek up over the height now crowned by the Du Pont and Nemours buildings, the army veered into West Street, marching as far as Fifth, thence right into Pasture Street, down which it marched towards Front. The camp of the First Brigade was on a line with Second Street, in an area, then open fields, now included between Justison and Adams Streets. The camp faced Front Street (and its extension, the Lancaster Pike) and was close to the road leading to Newport and Head of Elk (present Maryland Avenue), over which the troops would resume their march the next day.
      MS, No. 21-29. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 151]
    - 76. Camp à Head-of-Elk, le 7 Septembre, 20 miles de Willmington. Le 8 Sèjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-30)
      Thirtieth Camp at Head of Elk [in Maryland]. 7-8 September 1781. Twenty miles from the preceding camp at Wilmington. The First Brigade halted an extra day, so that both brigades were camped here together on the 8th, to the morth of the main road leading through the village of Head of Elk, or Elkton. Elk Landing, a mile or so south of the village, was on the "Head of Elk River" (formed by the confluence of Big Elk and Little Elk creeks) at one of the northernmost tips of the Chesapeake Bay to the Delaware River was largely eliminated by the completion in 1829 of the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal a few miles south.
      It was hoped that the armies, both French and American, could embark at Head of Elk and be ferried down the Bay to Virginia. In spite of Washington's efforts to have sufficient transport vessels assembled here. only a limited number of troops could be accomodated. These included a French detachment commanded by Colonel Custine; cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, nn. 89-90. These units are shown on the map close to the landing (within and below the letter "H" of "Head of Elk").
      The main part of the army thus continued its route towards Baltimore (and eventually Annapolis). The series of detailed road maps depicting the daily marches does not continue beyond Head of Elk, but the routes are schematically indicated on the comprehensive map of camps and marches, No. 162.
      The French army camped again at Elkton, by divisions, on 28-31 August 1782; see No. 134.
      MS, No. 21-30. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 151-152]
      Regarding Washington's efforts to assemble transport, see e.g. his letter to Governor Thomas Sim Lee of Maryland, 27 August 1781, in Writings of GW, XXIII, 57-58.
    - 77. Bivoüac à Lower-ferry, le 9 Septembre, 15 miles de Head of Elk, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-31)
      Bivouac at Lower Ferry. 9 September 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Head of Elk. After being ferried across the Susquehanna the four infantry regiments, as shown here, bivouacked together along the northern edge of the Baltimore road. "Lower Ferry" corresponds to the present Perryville-Havre de Grace crossing. ("Upper Ferry" was near Port Deposit.) The town of Havre de Grace did not exist in 1781, though when the French army passed over this route again in 1782 (No. 133) several officers noted in their journals that such a town was then being planned; see Verger's journal, n. 134. The "Tavern" shown on the map is presumably the "Ferry House" (later the Lafayette Hotel).
      No artillery units are shown on this map. The wagons and artillery, escorted by Lauzun's hussars under Colonel d'Arrot (the Duc de Lauzun himself and his Legion's infantry had embarked at Head of Elk), took a more circuitous route via Bald Friar Ford, which was some 7 miles upstream (above present Conowingo Dam). They camped at Cummings Tavern (Battle Swamp) east of the Susquehanna and, after the crossing by Bald Friar Ford, at "Dear Church" (Deer Creek Friends Meeting, Darlington) to the west of the river. Their route, via Churchville, then merged into that of the infantry at Bush. Clermont-Crèvecœur made this detour with the artillery, as described in his journal (p. 53 and nn. 92-93).
      MS, No 21-31. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 152]
    - 78. Bivoüac à Bush-Town, où Hartford, le 10 Septembre, 12 miles de Lower-ferry, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-32)
      Bivouac at Bush Town, or Harford. 10 September 1781. Twelve miles from Lower Ferry. Bush, originally called Harford Town, was the county seat of Harford County until 1783, when the seat was moved to Bel Air. Bush is still a small hamlet very similar in its general pattern to the one shown on this map. It is on the "old Philadelphia road," present State Route 7, which has now been superseded as the main traffic artery by parallel highways to the east (U.S. 40) and west (Interstate 95) of it. The stream flowing eastward (left of map), beyond which the infantry regiments bivouacked, is Bynum Run, a tributary of Bush River, which in turn flows into the Chesapeake Bay. The road coming into the main road from the right of the map (below letter "B" of "Bush Town") is the route (present Calvary Road) over which the artillery and wagons arrived from Bald Friar Ford. As recorded in Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal (p. 53), they reached Bush on 10 September, joining up the next day with the infantry regiments at a point beyond White Marsh.
      The following year the army camped again at Bush, by divisions, on 25-28 August 1782, in a slightly differnt position. Cf. No. 132.
      MS, No 21-32. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 152-153]
    - 79. Camp à White-Marsh, le 11 Septembre, 15 miles de Bush-Town, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-33)
      Thirty-third Camp at White Marsh. 11 September 1781. Two brigades, including the artillery, are shown. The distances noted in the headings of this and the following map indicate that this so-called White Marsh camp was 15 miles from Bush and 10 miles from the next camp in Baltimore. This would place the camp some 3 miles southwest of White March Forges (where the army camped on its northbound march in 1782, as shown on map, No. 131). The site was probably along the old Philadelphia road (State Route 7) near the corner of present Mohrs Lane. The stream shown on the map is a branch of White Marsh Run. The building across the road from the camp may be the mansion house of White Marsh Plantation, headquarters of the Nottingham Company, which managed the iron works at White Marsh Forges—or perhaps a tavern. Clermont-Crèvecœur (p. 54) places the camp at a "Tavern," which he does not identify by name.
      MS, No 21-33. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 153]
    - 80. Camp à Baltimore, le 12 Septembre, 10 miles de White-Marsh. Le 13, 14, 15 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-34)
      Thirty-fourth Camp at Baltimore. 12-15 September 1781. The street pattern shown on the map still underlies the section of modern Baltimore adjacent to the Basin, of "Port," as it is designated here. North is at the right of the map, west at the top. Charles Street runs along the west side of the "Port"; above it (running diagonally) is Liberty Street. The street running west to east through the middle of the grid is Market (now Baltimore) Street. The stream flowing from the north into the Basin is Jones's Falls; below it is Old Town, next is a depression known as the Harford Run, then a street (Point Lane, now Broadway) leading out to Fell's Point (not named on the map).
      One brigade (the Soissonnais and Saintonge, with artillery) is shown to the left (south) of the "chemin de Spurier's Tavern," i.e., the road (approximately U.S. Route 1) leading to Georgetown; on a height to the right (north) of this road are more artillery and wagons, as well as two other units (including Lauzun's hussars, indicated by the cartographer's customary symbol for cavalry). Another brigade (the Bourbonnais and Duex-Ponts, with artillery) was camped in Old Town, east of Jones's Falls, in readiness for embarkation.
      The expected embarkation did not take place at Baltimore. Again, as at Head of Elk, transports proved inadequate; cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, n. 98, and also Matthew Ridley's letter to Governor Lee, 9 September 1781, conveying Washington's urgent request "for collecting Vessels from all parts" at Baltimore. Thereupon the army, now under the command of the Baron de Viomenil (Rochambeau having proceeded ahead with Washington overland to Williamsburg), resumed its march on 16 September, bound for Georgetown and Alexandria on the Potomac. Upon reaching the next camp at Spurrier's Tavern, news of the arrival of La Villebrune's squadron at Annapolis determined a countermarch back to the shores of the Chesapeake Bay.
      MS, No 21-34. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 153-154]
      Ridley's letter to Governer Lee can be found in Archives of Maryland, Vol. XLVII: Journal and Correspondence of the State Council of Maryland (Letters to the Governor and Council), 7, 1781, ed. J. Hall Pleasants (Baltimore, 1930), pp. 482-483.
    - 85. Camp à Arche's-Hupe, le 25 Septembre, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-35/38)
      Thirty-Eighth Camp at Archer's Hope. 25 September 1781. The transports that had brought the combined French and American forces from Annapolis are shown off the landing point at Archer's Hope, which was about 7 miles southeast of Williamsburg to the west of the mouth of College Creek. Washington (Diaries, II, 261) refers to the spot as "the upper point of College Creek." The present Colonial Parkway passes along this shore. Archer's Hope is east of Jamestown Island, where Saint-Simon's forces from the West Indies had landed on 2 September. About 3 1/2 miles downstream and east of Archer's Hope encampment, depicted here near the shore along the road leading to Williamsburg, shows both French regiments (yellow) and the American units (green).
      MS, No 21-35/38. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 156-157]
    - 86. Camp à Williamsburg, le 26 Septembre, 7 miles de Arche's-Hupe. Le 27 Séjour, undated; 1 item 32 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-39)
      Thirty-ninth Camp at Williamsburg. The road from Archer's Hope over which the army marched to its positions "at the gates of Williamsburg" is at the lower center of the map (below the word "Rich-mill's"). Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal (p. 56) notes that the field artillery was brought up College Creek in boats and unloaded at College Landing (lower right of map). The new arrivals found Saint Simon's regiments already encamped to the northwest of the town (lower left, tinted yellow) and Lafayette's Americans (tinted green) west and south of the College of William and Mary. The French detachment that had been brought from Newport in Barras's squadron was also in camp (cf. Verger's journal, p. 137), as was the vanguard under Custine that had enbarked at Head of Elk. Rochambeau's regiments (tinted yellow) made their camp to the east of town behind the Capitol, while Washington's Americans (tinted green) took a position farther to the south. The encampment at Williamsburg marked the 39th camp of Rochambeau's army since its departure from its 1st camp at Providence, Rhode Island, on 18 June. This map is the last in the "cahier" of the 1781 camps. [The 40th and final camp of this "campaign," showing the siege of Yorktown, referred to at the bottom of the sheet, is reproduced in the Rice/Brown volume but is not part of the Berthier Papers at Princeton.]
      MS, No 21-39. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 157]
  - Journal du Siége d'Yorck en Virginie, undated; 1 item 16 pp Manuscript. Last 6 pages blank. (Portfolio X, Packet 22)
    "Description of the Siege of Yorktown, Sept. 28 - Oct. 19, 1781"
  - Capitulation du Siege d'Yorck Le 19 8bre, undated; 1 item 12 pp Manuscript. Last 8 pages blank. (Portfolio X, Packet 23)
    "Articles of Capitulation, Yorktown, October 19, 1781"
  - Prisonniers et pertes faittes a Yorck et à Glocester le 19 8bre, 1781, undated; 1 item 2 pp manuscript (Portfolio X, Packet 24)
    "Table of Prisoners and Losses of the English at Yorktown, 1781"
  - Compliment de Son Excellence le Gal Washington a l'armée combineé, 1781 October, undated; 1 item 6 pp Manuscript. 3 pages blank. (Portfolio X, Packet 25)
    "Copy of Washington's Message of Congratulation to the Combined French and American Armies at Yorktown"
  - Extrait des Opérations de la campagne de l'armée combinée Française et Amèricaine, 1781, undated; 1 item 12 pp Manuscript. 4 pages blank. (Portfolio XI, Packet 26)
    "Recapitulation of the Operations of the Combined French and American Armies, 1781"
  - Précis de La Campagne de L'armée navale aux ordres du comte de Grasse, 1781, undated; 1 item 8 pp (Portfolio III, Packet 27)
    "Précis of the Naval Operations under De Grasse, 1781".
- Series 3: Winter Quarters of the French Army in Virginia, 1781-1782, 1781 October-1782 April 5; portions of 2 portfolios
  Different documents for the period beginning after the victory of Yorktown and extending until the following July 1782, when the northward march was begun.
  Arranged sequentially by packet/item number.
  Descriptions for the maps have been taken verbatim from Howard C. Rice and Anne S. K. Brown, The American Campaigns of Rochambeau's Army (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1972), Volume 2. Leading numbers in the map titles correspond to numbers assigned to the maps by Rice and Brown; these numbers are used in their descriptions to refer to other Berthier maps. (The actual Bethier number for the map is provided at the end of each description.) Gaps in the Rice-Brown numbers reflect the fact that they also draw from other sources in their work (i.e., also describe other maps). Measurements, in centimeters, give the size of the sheets.
  - 106. Plan d'Hampton pour servir a l'Etablissement du Quartier d'hiver de la Legion de L'auzun, le 1 9bre, 1781, undated; 1 item 39 x 31.5 cm (on 42.5 x 36 cm sheet) (Portfolio X, Packet 28)
    Plan of Hampton [in Virginia] to be Used for Establishing the Winter Quarters of Lauzun's Legion. 1 November 1781. The stream at the right, flowing south, is the Hampton River. The other directional arrow, at the left of the map below the legend, is misleading (probably a mistake); the point indicates south, not the customary north. Directly below this arrow point indicates south, not the customary north. Directly below this arrow point is St. John's Episcopal Chruch. The two longest streets forming a cross are King Street (from top to bottom of map) and Queen Street (left to right). The numbers indicating available lodgings were presumably used for assigning quarters. The billeting list that might supply a key to these numbers is not preserved with the map and has not been found.
    When steps were being taken to quarter his army early in November 1781, Rochabeau assured the local authorities that a barrack master approved by Governor Nelson and by General Washington would proceed in such a way as to cause minimum expense to the inhabitants and that necessary repairs to war-damaged houses would be made at the King's expense; cf. his letter to the Council of the City of Williansburg, printed in Doniol, V, 584-585. According to Von Closen (p. 162), the winter quarters, into which the troops moved on 15-18 November, were assigned as follows: the Bourbonnais Regiment, seven companies of the Royal Deux-Ponts, part of the Auxonne artillery, as well as the General Staff, were quartered in Williamsburg. Three companies of the Royal Deux-Ponts were sent to Jamestown. The Soissonnais, with the grenadiers and chasseurs of the Saintonge, were at Yorktown (see No. 99). The Saintonge Regiment encamped at Halfway House (on the road from Yorktown to Hampton) and Back River. A detachment of 50 men and an artillery company was assigned to Gloucester. The rest of the artillery went to West Point at the head of York River (see No. 104). Finally, Lauzun's Legion took up quarters in Hampton, as confirmed by the present map.
    The Lauzun Legion did not remain here at Hampton during the entire period of the "winter quarters." In early February 1782 Rochambeau sent the Legion under the command of General Choisy (Lauzun having returned temporarily to France) to an advanced position near the North Carolina border at the request of General Nathanael Greene, who feard the arrival of British reinforcements at Charleston. The Legion remained in the vicinity of Charlotte Courthouse until June, when it retired to Petersburg and eventually rejoined the main body of the army on its northward march. After the Legion's departure from Hampton a battalion of the Saintonge Regiment moved into quarters there.